the
topic I've been talking I've been
multiplying matrices already but
certainly time for me to discuss the
rules for matrix multiplication and the
interesting part is the many ways you
can do it and they all give the same
answer so it's and they're all important
so matrix multiplication and then uh
come inverses so we're we we mentioned
the inverse of a matrix but there's
that's a big deal lots to do about
inverses and how to find them okay so
I'll begin with how to multiply two
matrices first way okay so suppose I
have a
matrix
a multiplying a matrix B
and giving me a result well I could call
it C A * B
okay uh so let me just review the rule
for for this entry that's the entry in
row I and column J so that's the IJ
entry right there is CI
J we always write the row number and
then the column number so I might I
might maybe I take it
c34 just to make it specific so instead
of i j let me use numbers
c34 so where does that come from the 34
entry it comes from Row three here Row
three and column
four as you know column four and can I
just write down or can we write down the
formula for it
c34
is if we look at the whole row and the
whole whole column the quick way for me
to say it is Row 3 of a I could use a
DOT for dotproduct I won't often use
that actually dot column 4 of
B and but this gives us a chance to just
like use a little Matrix not
ation what are the entries what's this
first entry in Row three the first the
first that number that's sitting right
there
is a so it's got two indices and what
are they 31 so there's an a 31 there now
what's the first guy at the top of
column
4 so what what's sitting up there B4
four
right so that this dot product starts
with a 31 *
b14 and then what's the next so this is
like I'm accumulating this sum then
comes the next guy
a32 second column times
B24 second row so it's B
a32 B24 and so on
just practice with indices oh let let me
even practice with the a summation
formula so this is I
I most of the course I use whole vectors
I very seldom uh get down to the details
of these particular entries but here we
better do it so I'm it's some kind of a
sum right of things in Row three
column K shall I
say times things
in row K column 4 you see that that's
what's that's what we're seeing here
this is K is
one here K is two on along so up so the
sum goes all the way along the row and
down the column say one to n so that's
what the a the c34 entry looks like like
a sum of a 3 k b K4 just takes a little
practice to do
that okay and uh oh well maybe I should
say when are we allowed to multiply
these matrices what are the shapes of
these things the shapes are uh if we
allow them to be not necessarily Square
matrices if they're Square they've got
to be the same size if they're
rectangular they're not the same size if
they're rectangular this might be well I
always think of a as m
byn m rows n columns so that sum goes to
n now what's the point how many rows
does B have to
have n n the number of rows in B the
number of guys that we meet coming down
has to match the number of ones across
so B will have to be n by something
whatever
P so the the number of columns here has
to match the number of rows there and
then what's the result what's the shape
of the result what's the shape of C the
output well it's got these same M rows
or it's got M rows and how many
columns
p m by P okay so they're m time P Little
Numbers in there entries and each one
looks like that okay so that's the
standard rule that's the way people
think of multiplying
matrices
um I do it
too but that's that's I I want to talk
about other ways to look at that same
calculation uh looking at whole columns
and whole rows
okay so can I do ab C again a equaling C
again but now tell me tell me
about
uh yeah let me I'll put it up
here so here goes a
again time
B
producing
C and again this is is M
byn this is n by P and this is M by P
okay now I want to look at whole
columns I I want to look at The Columns
of in fact here's the second way to
multiply
matrices cuz I'm going to build on what
I know already how do I multiply a
matrix by a column how do I I I know how
to multiply this matrix by that column
shall I call that column
one that tells me column one of the
answer the Matrix times the First Column
is that First
Column cuz none of this stuff entered
that part of the answer the Matrix times
the second column is the second column
of the answer do you see what I'm saying
that I could think of multiplying a
matrix by a vector which I already knew
how to do
and I can think of the V I can think of
just P columns sitting side by side just
like resting next to each
other and I multiply a times each one of
those and I get the P Columns of the
answer do you see this is this is quite
nice to be able to think
okay matrix multiplication works so that
I could just think of having several
columns multiplying by a and getting The
Columns of the answer so like here's
column
one I call that here's a shall I call
that column
one and what's going in there is a *
column
1 okay so that's the picture a column at
a time so what does that tell me what
does that tell me about these columns
these Columns of
c
are
combinations as we've seen that
before
of
columns
a every one of these comes from a * this
and a * a vector is a combination of The
Columns of a and right and it makes
sense because The Columns of a have
length M and The Columns of C have
length M and every column of C is a is
some combination of The Columns of a and
it's these numbers in here that tell me
what combination it is do you see
that that that out that in that answer C
I'm seeing stuff that's col that's
combinations of these columns now
suppose I look at it that's two ways now
the Third Way is look at it by
rows so now let me change to
rows okay so now I can think of a row of
a a a row of a multiplying all these
rows here and producing a row of the the
product so this row takes a combination
of these rows and that's the answer so
these
rows of
c
are
combinations of
what
of tell me about to finish that the rows
of C when I when I I have a matrix B
it's got its rows and I multiply by
a and what does that do it mixes the
rows up it makes it creates combinations
of the rows of B thanks rows of
B that's what I wanted to
see that this that this
answer I can see where the pieces are
coming from the rows in the answer are
coming as combinations of these rows the
columns in the answer are com coming as
combinations of of those columns and now
that so that's three ways now you can
say okay what's the fourth way the
fourth
way so that's now we've got like the
regular way the column way the row way
and what's left
uh
the the one that I can I I want to tell
you about well one way is columns times
rows what
happens if I multiply so this was row
time column it gave a
number okay now I want to ask you about
column times row what does If I multiply
a column
of
a times a row of
B what shape am I ending up with so if I
take a column times a
row that's definitely different from
taking a row times a column so a column
of a was what what's the shape of a
column of
a m
by one a column of a is is a column
it's got M entries and one coln and
what's a row of B it's got one
row and P column so what's the shap what
do I get if I multiply a column by a
row I get a big Matrix I get a fullsize
matrix If I multiply a column by a row I
get should we just do
one let me take the the column 2 3
4times the Row 1
6 that is a that product there I I'm
just following the rules of matrix
multiplication those rules are just
looking like kind of petique kind of
small because the the rows here are so
short and the columns there are so short
but they're the same length one in so
what's the answer
what's the answer if I do 234 * 1 16
just for practice well what's the first
row of the
answer
212 and the second row of the answer
is
318 and the third row of the answer is
424 actually what am I I mean that's a
very special Matrix there
very special Matrix what can you tell me
about its columns The Columns of that
Matrix they're multiples of this guy
right they're multiples of that one
which follows our rule we said that the
columns of the answer were combinations
but there's only to take a combination
of one guy it's just a multiple the rows
of the answer what can you tell me about
those three
rows they're all multip multiples of
this row they're all multiples of six as
we expect but I'm getting a full siiz
Matrix and now just to complete this
thought if I
have uh now let me write down the Fourth
Way
AB is a sum
of columns of a
times rows of
B so that for example if my if my Matrix
was 2 3 4 and then had another column
say 7 8
9 and my Matrix here has say started
with
six and then had another column like 0
0 then
here's the fourth way okay I've got two
columns there I've got two rows there so
the beautiful rule
is seeing the whole thing by columns and
rows is that I can take the First
Column times the first
row and add the second column times the
second row
so that's the fourth way that that I can
take columns times rows First Column
time first row second column time second
row and add actually what will I get
what will the answer be for that matrix
multiplication well this one is just
going to give us zero so in fact I'm
back to this that's the answer for that
matrix multiplication
I'm I'm sort of like happy to put up
here these facts about matrix
multiplication because it gives me a
chance to write down special matrices
like this this is a special Matrix uh
all those rows lie on the same
line all those rows lie on the line
through one six if I draw a picture of
all these row vectors they're all the
same
direction if I draw a picture of these
two column vectors they're in the same
direction later I would use this
language not too much later either I
would say the row space which is like
all the combinations of the rows is just
a line for this Matrix the row space is
the line through the vector six all the
rows lie on that
line and the column space is also a line
all the columns l y on the line through
the vector 2 3 4 so this is like a
really minimal Matrix and it's because
of these
ones okay so that's a third way now even
yeah I can I when you will you take this
is I I want to say one more thing about
matrix multiplication while we're on
this
subject and it's this you could also
multiply you can also cut the Matrix
into
blocks and do the multiplication by
blocks yeah that that's actually so
uh useful that I that I want to uh
mention it block
multiplication so I could take my Matrix
a and I could chop it up like maybe just
for Simplicity let me chop it into two
into Four Square block suppose it's
Square let's just take a nice case and B
suppose it's Square
also same
size though these sizes don't have to be
the same what they have to do is match
properly here they certainly will match
so here's the rule for Block
multiplication that if this has blocks
like uh uh a so maybe A1 A2 A3 A4 are
the blocks here and these blocks are B1
B2 B3 and
B4 then the answer I can find block I
can find that block and if you tell me
what's in that block then I'm going to
be quiet about matrix multiplication for
the rest of the
day what goes into that
block you see these might be this Matrix
might be these matrices might be like 20
by
20 with blocks that are 10 by 10 to take
the easy case where all the blocks are
the same
shape and the point is that I could
multiply those by blocks and what goes
in here what's that what's that what's
that block in the answer A1
B1 that's a matrix times a matrix it's
the right size 10 by 10 anymore
Plus what's the what what what else goes
in
there A2 B3 right it's just like block
rows times block
columns I don't nobody I think not even
gaus could see instantly that it
works but somehow if we check it through
all five ways were're doing the same
multiplications so this this familiar
multiplication is what we're really
doing when we do it by columns by rows
by columns times rows and by
blocks okay I just have to like get the
rules straight for matrix
multiplication
okay all right I'm ready for the second
topic which is
inverses okay ready for
inverse and let me do it for square
matrices
first okay so I've got a square Matrix
a
and and it may or may not have an
inverse right not all matrices have
inverses in fact like that's the most
important
question you can ask about the Matrix is
if it's square if you know it's
square is it invertible or not if it is
invertible then then there is some other
Matrix shall I call it a
inverse and what's
the what's if a inverse exists so this
is if there's a big if here if this
Matrix exists
and and it'll be really Central to
figure out when does it exist and then
if it does exist how would you find it
but what's the what's the the equation
here that I haven't uh that I have to
finish now this Matrix if it exists
multiplies a and
produces I thanks the
identity and actually there's a little
more to
it because
normally I mean that right now that's
like a left inverse it's sitting on the
left of
X but a real an inverse for a square
Matrix could be on the right as well so
so uh this is true
too that it if I have a yeah in fact
this is not this is probably
the this is something that's not
easy to prove but it
works that a left that for square
matrices a left inverse is also a right
inverse if I can find a matrix on the
left that gets the identity then also
that Matrix on the right will produce
that
identity for rectangular matrices we'll
see a left inverse that isn't a right
inverse in fact the shapes wouldn't
allow it but for square matrices the
shapes allow it and it
happens if a has an inverse okay so give
me some
cases let's see I hate to be negative
here but let's talk about the case with
no
inverse so so this is this is these
matrices are called invertible
or non
singular those are the good
ones and we want to be able to identify
how if we're given a matrix has it got
an inverse can I talk about the singular
case no
inverse all right uh best to start with
an
example tell me an example let's let's
get an example up here let's make it 2x
two of a matrix that has not got an
inverse and let's see
why let me let me write one
up no inv let's let's see why let me
write up 1326
why does that Matrix have no
inut you could you could answer that
various
ways uh Give Me One
Reason well you could if you know about
determinant which you're not supposed
to uh you could take its determinant and
you would get
zero
okay now all
right let me let me ask you other
reasons let me ask for other reasons
that that Matrix isn't
invertible here I could use use what I'm
saying here suppose
um suppose a times some other Matrix
gave the identity
why is that not
possible
because yeah tell I'm I'm thinking about
columns Here If I multiply this Matrix a
by some other Matrix then the the the
result what can you tell me about the
column they're
all multiples of those columns right if
I multiply a by another Matrix that the
product has columns that come from those
columns so can I get the identity Matrix
no way The Columns of the identity
Matrix like one Z it's not a combination
of those columns because those two
columns lie on the both lie on the same
line every combination is just going to
be on that line and I can't get one zero
so do you see do you see that
that sort of column picture of the
Matrix not being invertible in fact
here's another
reason oh this is even a more important
reason well how can I say more important
all those are
important this is another way to see
it a matrix has no
inverse yeah here now this is
important a matrix has no a square
Matrix won't have an inverse
if there's
if no inverse because I can solve I can
find an
x a a a vector
x
with a * this a * X giving
zero that this is the reason Reon I like
best that Matrix won't have an inverse
can you well let me change I to
U so tell me a vector
X that uh solves ax equals z i mean this
is like the key equation in mathematics
all the key equations have zero on the
right hand side so what's the s tell
tell me an X here so now I'm going to
put slip in the x that you tell me and
I'm going to get
zero what what x would do that
job 3 and negative
1 is that the one you picked or yeah or
or another Well if you pick zero and
zero I'm not so excited right CU that
would always work so it's all it's
really the fact that this Vector isn't
zero is important
it's a nonzero vector and 31 would do it
that just says three of this column
minus one of that column is the zero
column
okay so now I know that uh a couldn't be
invertible what what's the what's the
reasoning if if ax is zero suppose I
multiplied by a inverse yeah here's the
reason here here this is why
This spells disaster for an inverse a
matrix can't have an inverse if some
combination of the columns gives gives
nothing
because I could take axal z i could
multiply by a
inverse and what would I
discover suppose I take that equation
and I multiply by I if a inverse existed
which of course I'm going to come to the
conclusion it can
cuz if it existed if there was an a
inverse to this Dopey Matrix I would
multiply that equation by that inverse
and I would
discover X is zero If I multiply a by a
inverse on the left I get X If I
multiply by a inverse on the right I get
zero so I would discover X was Zero but
if X is not Zer X this guy wasn't zero
there it is 3 - one
so
conclusion only take us some time to
really work with that conclusion our
conclusion will be that that in that
that noninvertible matrixes singular
matrices some combinations of their some
combination of their columns gives the
zero
column they they take some Vector X into
zero and there's no way a inverse been
recovered right that's what this
equation says this equation says I take
this Vector X and multiplying by a gives
zero but then when I multiply by a
inverse I can never escape from zero so
there couldn't be an a
inverse where
here okay now fix all right now let me
take a all right back to the positive
side let's take a Matrix that does have
an
inverse and why not invert it okay can I
so let me take on this third board a
matrix so I fix that up a
little uh tell me a matrix that has got
an
inverse well let me say 1 3 2 what
should I put
there well don't put six I guess
right you want any any favorites
here
one or
eight I don't care seven seven okay
seven is a lucky all right seven
okay okay so now what's our idea we
believe that this Matrix is inverted
those who like determinants have quickly
taken its determinant and found it
wasn't zero those are like columns and
probably that that department is not
totally popular yet but those are like
columns we'll look at those two columns
and say hey they point in different
directions
so I can get anything now let let me see
what do I mean how am I going to compute
a inverse so a
inverse here's a
inverse and I have to find it
and and what do I get when I'm when I do
this
multiplication the
identity you know forgive me for taking
2 by two but like it's good to keep the
computations
manageable and let the ideas come out
Okay now what's the idea I
want I'm looking for this Matrix a
inverse how am I going to find it right
now it's uh I've got four numbers to
find I'm going to look at the First
Column let me take this First Column
a what's up
there what equation yeah tell me this
what equation does the First Column
satisfy the First Column satisfies a *
that column is 1
Z the First Column of the
answer and the second column
CD satisfies a * that second column is
01 do you see
that finding the inverse is like solving
two
systems one system when the right hand
side is one zero I'm just going to split
it into two
pieces that I don't I don't even need to
rewrite it I can I can take a time so
let me put it
here
A times
column J of a
inverse is column
J of the
identity I've got in equations I've got
well two in this
case and they have the same Matrix a but
they have different right hand sides the
right hand sides are just The Columns of
the identity this guy and this guy and
these are the two solutions do you do
you see what I'm doing I'm looking at
that
equation by columns I'm looking at a *
this column giving that guy and a * that
column giving that guy
so essentially so this is like the
gaus we're back to gaus we're back to
solving systems of equations but we're
solving we've got two right hand sides
instead of
one that's where Jordan comes in so so
at the very beginning of the lecture I
mentioned gal Jordan let me write it up
again okay here's the
Gus Jordan
idea g j
is
solves
solve two equations at
once okay let me show you how the how
the mechanics
go H how do I solve
a a single equation so the two equations
are
uh
1327 multiplying a
gives 1
Z and the other equation is the same
1327 multiplying
CD gives
okay that'll tell me the two columns of
the inverse I'll have the inverse in
other words if I can solve with this
Matrix a if I can solve with that right
hand side and that right hand side I'm
inverted
I've got it okay and the and Jordan sort
of said to
G solve them together look at the Matrix
if we just solve this one I would look
at 13
27 and how do I deal with the right hand
side I stick it on as an extra column
right you remember that's that's this
augment Matrix that's the Matrix when
I'm watching the right hand side at the
same time doing the same thing to the
right side that I do to the left so I
just carry it along as an extra column
now I'm going to carry along two extra
columns and I'm going to do whatever gal
wants right I'm going to do
elimination I'm going to get this to be
simple and this this thing will turn
into the inverse this is what's
coming I'm going to do elimination steps
to make this into the
identity and lo and behold the inverse
will show up
here let's do it okay so what are the
elimination
steps so you see that here's my Matrix a
and here's the identity like stuck on
augmented
on suppos to be switched did I oh no
they weren't supposed to be switched
sorry
thanks okay thank you very
much and there I've got them right okay
thanks okay so let's do elimination all
right it's going to be simple right so I
take two of this row away from this row
so this row stays the
same and two of those come away from
this that leads me with a zero and a one
and two of these away from this is that
what that is that what you're
getting after one elimination step I let
me sort of separate the the left half
from the right half so two of that first
row got subtracted from the second row
now now this is an upper triangular
form gaus would quit but Jordan says
keep going you use elimination upwards
subtract a multiple of equation two from
equation one to to get rid of the three
so let's go the whole way so now I'm
going to this guy is
fine but I'm going to what do I do now
what's my final step that that produces
the inverse I multiply this by the right
number to get up to there to to to
remove that three so I guess since since
this is a one there's the pivot sitting
there I multiply it by three and
subtract from that so what do I get I'll
have one zero oh yeah that was my whole
point I'll multiply this by three and
subtract from that which will give
me
7 and I multiply this by three and
subtract from that which gives me a
minus three
and what's
my hope
belief here here I started with with a
and the identity and I ended up with the
identity and
who that better be a
inverse that's the gaus Jordan idea
start start with this long Matrix double
length
AI eliminate eliminate until this part
is down to I then this one will must be
for some reason and we got to find the
reason must be a
inverse shall I just check that it
works let me just check that can I
multiply this
Matrix this this part times a I'll carry
a over here
here and just do that multiplication
you'll see I'll do it the oldfashioned
way 7 - 6 is a 1 21 - 21 is a 0 - 2 + 2
is a 0 - 6 + 7 is a 1
check so that is the
inverse that's the gaus Jordan idea so
you'll one of the homework problems or
more than one uh for Wednesday will ask
you to go through those
steps I think you just got to go through
gaus Jordan a couple of
times but so I like
yeah just to see the
mechanics but the important thing is why
is like what happened why did we why did
we get a
inverse let me ask you that
[Music]
we
got so we take we we do row reduction we
do elimination on this long Matrix
AI until the first half is
up then the second half is a inverse
well how do I see that let me put up
here how I see that so here's my here's
my Gus Jordan thing and and I'm doing
stuff to
it so
I'm well whole lot of
ease remember those are those
elimination Matrix those are the those
are the things that we figured out last
time yes that's what an elimination step
is is it's it's in Matrix form I'm
multiplying by some e and the result
well so I'm multiplying by a whole bunch
of e so I get a can I call the overall
Matrix
e that's the elimination Matrix the
product of all those little pieces what
do I mean by little pieces well there
was an elimination Matrix that
subtracted two of that away from that
then there was an elimination Matrix
that subtracted three of that away from
that I I guess in this case that was all
so there were just two e in this case
one that did this step and one that did
this step and together they give me an e
that does both
steps
and the net result was to get an I here
and you can tell me what that has to
be this is like the the picture of what
happened if e multiplied a whatever that
e is we never figured it out in in by by
by in this way but whatever that e *
that e is e * a
is what's E *
a it's a that e whatever the heck it was
multiplied a and produce
I so e must be EA equally I tells us
what e is namely it
is it's the inverse of a
great and therefore when the second half
when e multiplies I it's e but that's a
inverse you see the the picture looking
that way e * a is the
identity that tells us what e has to be
it has to be the inverse and therefore
on the right hand side where e where we
just smartly tucked on the identity it's
turning in step by step it's turning
into a
invers there is
the the statement of G Jordan
elimination that's how you find the
inverse we're we look we can look at it
as
elimination at solving n equations at
the same time and packing on N columns
solving those equations and up shows the
end Columns of a okay thanks St ready